Guide to the Elizabeth E. Smith Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Elizabeth E. Smith papers
1883-1885
MS 1108
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2
Travel journals written by Elizabeth E. Smith on a trip to Europe and the Near East (1883-1885). The copious journals record not only architecture and the arts, but also the daily life and customs of the people whom she observed. Included in the journals are also photographs, prints, newspaper clippings, and drawings, some of them her own. Also in the papers are several of her poems and essays written during the trip.
Smith, Elizabeth E.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of A. Stuart Pitt, 1939.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
Elizabeth E. Smith's papers consist of travel journals compiled from 1883 to 1885 during her third extended tour from New York to Europe and the Near East. A well-educated, observant woman interested in history and art, she presents a well-written narrative of what she saw and experienced while traveling with her sister, brother-in-law, and nieces through England to Russia, south through Central Europe to Italy, Spain, and Morocco, and then east to Greece and the Levant. She was very attentive not only to architecture and the arts but also to the daily life and customs of the common people whose countries she traversed, describing in detail religious practices and local costumes as well as art galleries and the usual tourist sights. Her journals are profusely illustrated with photographs, prints, newspaper clippings, and drawings, some of which she drew herself.
The papers are completed by several manuscript poems and essays written by Elizabeth Smith during her trip.
Architecture; Art; Women; Austria -- Description and travel; Belgium -- Description and travel; Europe -- Description and travel; France -- Description and travel; Germany -- Description and travel; Italy -- Description and travel; Middle East -- Description and travel; Poland -- Description and travel; Soviet Union -- Description and travel; Spain -- Description and travel; Switzerland -- Description and travel; Turkey -- Description and travel; Diaries; Poems; Smith, Elizabeth E.
- Inventory
  - Travel journals
    - England, 1883 May 5-July 15 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Norway, Sweden, Finland, Russia, 1883 August 24-October 9 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Russia, 1883 October 10-November 2 (Box 1, Folder 3 - 4)
    - Russia, Poland, Austria, 1883 November 3-20 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Austria, Italy, 1883 December 2-13 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Italy, 1883 December 14-1884 February (Box 2, Folder 7 - 13)
    - Italy, 1884 March 1-10 (Box 3, Folder 14 - 15)
    - Italy, Spain, 1884 March 10-28 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Spain, 1884 March 31-April (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Morocco, Spain, 1884 May-June 18 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Spain, France, 1884 June 21-July 4 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - France, Switzerland, 1884 July 6-14 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Switzerland, 1884 July 20-September 27 (Box 3, Folder 21 - 22)
    - Switzerland, Germany, Belgium, 1884 October 4-26 (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Belgium, Holland, Geramny, 1884 October 20-November 24 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Germany, 1884 November 30-December 7 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Austria, Greece, Turkey, 1884 December 13-22 (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Egypt, Palestine, Syria, Lebanon, 1885 January-May (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - "Diary of Poems, Europe", 1883-1884 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Essays, undated (Box 5, Folder 29 - 30)